# 二伯好
Hello, Er Bai
# 大爷好
Hello, Da Ye
# 今天二伯给我们弄一个啥好菜
What are you bringing us today, Er Bai?
# 这菜可有年头了
There is some history behind today’s dish
# 这菜我得重点讲讲
Which I’d like to talk about
# 这菜叫什么
What is it called?
# 无锡排骨
Wuxi Pork Ribs
# 无锡排骨 我了解
I know Wuxi Pork Ribs
# 江苏菜
It’s a Jiangsu dish
# 淮扬菜
Huaiyang dish
# 大爷今天我做这版
Da Ye, the version I’m cooking today
# 可不是淮扬菜
Is not actually a Huaiyang dish
# 港式无锡排骨
It’s Wuxi Pork Ribs in Hong Kong style
# 建国饭店第一任大厨黄金元
It was developed by the First Chef of Jianguo Hotel, Huang Jinyuan
# 后来到了天伦王朝
He later became the chef at Sunworld Dynasty (Hotel)
# 我跟他做搭档
And I was his culinary partner
# 他的原方我给呈现过来
Today I’m going to replicate his original recipe
# 在天伦的时候我们俩做搭档
I learned this when we partnered at Sunworld Dynasty
# 这个方是他的原方
This is his original recipe
# 今天我得好好看看
I shall open my eyes today
# 这个港式的无锡排骨
To see how this Hong Kong style Wuxi Pork Ribs
# 跟淮扬的无锡排骨有哪些区别
Differs from the traditional Huaiyang version
# 开始吧二伯
Let’s start, Er Bai
# 大爷您看啊
Watch closely, Da Ye
# 你可准备好我可挖坑了
Get ready, as I have dug the hole
# 挖坑吧大爷
Take your time, Da Ye
# 介绍一下原料吧 师父
Tell us about the ingredients, master
# 香叶
Bay leaves
# 桂皮
Cinnamon
# 八角草果
Star anise and tsao-ko
# 这个料是提香的
They are for aroma
# 少量的冰糖
Small amount of rock sugar
# 这是番茄酱
Tamato sauce
# 这是蜂蜜
Honey
# 香醋
Zhenjiang vinegar
# 这个呢 OK汁
And this is OK Sauce
# 这个喼汁
Worcestershire Sauce
# 配料 彩椒葱头
Other ingredients include bell peppers and onions
# 这是您的老贯口啊
These are your favourites
# 最后还有一个什么
Last but not the least
# 您(做)淮扬菜您知道
You must know this as you cook a lot of Huaiyang dishes
# 这个红曲米啊
This is red yeast rice
# 大爷还真不是说提粤菜夸张
Da Ye, I’m not exaggerating Cantonese food
# 这个港式的还真是不一样
But this Hong Kong style is really different
# 大爷您看很简单
Da Ye, it’s quite simple
# 你看我这排骨呢 看着还挺新鲜
Look at these fresh pork ribs
# 这个不用焯
We don’t need to parboil them
# 一焯这排骨就没那么香了
Otherwise they won’t be as fragrant
# 就直接炸 大爷
We deep fry them straight away, Da Ye
# 油温差不多了
The oil temperature is about right
# 好
Nice
# 一看就有六成热
It looks like 60% hot (180 degree centigrade)
# 油温低了不行
The oil temperature can’t be low
# 慢慢的沁炸 香气味出来了
Fry them slowly to bring out the aroma
# 这个脏腥味就没了
And the gamey smell is also gone
# 所以说我们没必要
That’s why I don’t think
# 再出水了
That we need to parboil them
# 这样烧出来的肉更香大爷
The pork ribs will be more fragrant when cooking like this, Da Ye
# 这个方法
This
# 是我们传统的一个烹调方法
Is a very traditional way of cooking meat
# 你像过去的烧鸭块儿烧鸡块儿都要炸
When we braise duck or chicken, we also fry them first
# 现在也是大火
It’s still on high heat
# 大爷你看是吧
What do you think, Da Ye?
# 慢慢让它就上色
We colour the pork slowly
# 这个不怕炸
They sustain the heat rather well
# 时间长了会不会把肉给炸老了呢
Will the pork be overcooked if we fry them for too long?
# 不会
No, they won’t
# 因为我还得拿高压锅压
Because I will braise them in the high-pressure cooker later
# 这就熟了大爷
Now it’s done, Da Ye
# 好 捞出
Take them out
# 下一步咱开始了
Next
# 咱把这香料掰一下
Let’s snap these aromatics
# 桂皮 香叶
Cinnamon, bay leaves
# 草果 搁一个就够
One piece of tsao-ko
# 八角 煸一煸
Star anise. Fry them gently
# 大爷您看
Look, Da Ye
# 所有的料都给它搁下去就行了
We put in all other ingredients
# 葱姜
Spring onions, ginger
# 胡萝卜
Carrots
# 芹菜
Celeries
# 还有洋葱
And onions
# 都下锅了
All in the wok
# 因为我们这肉一般都是属于酸性的
As we know, meats are normally acidic
# 所以二伯每次在做肉菜当中
So whenever Er Bai cooks a meat dish
# 放了一些素菜
He will add in some vegetables
# 香菜
Coriander
# 素菜属于碱性
Vegetables are alkaline
# 它的酸碱平衡
So the dish is balanced between acidity and alkalinity
# 而且又增加了美味
And it becomes even more flavoursome
# 你看啊
Look
# 看着就好吃 还没吃呢
They look so tasty already
# 然后咱们下料了啊
Then, we add
# 黄酒
Yellow rice wine
# 爆香
And bring out the aroma
# 这叫烹调
This is what we call ‘cooking’
# 你看小魏 香气味够了吧
Look, Xiao Wei, isn’t it fragrant?
# 现在我们再炒这个
Now let’s fry other ingredients
# 番茄沙司100克
100g of tamato sauce
# OK汁
OK Sauce
# OK汁 你看也100克
Also 100g
# 为什么这个排骨这味道它特殊啊
That’s something that gives this dish its unique flavour
# (OK汁) 西餐常用
OK Sauce is commonly used in Western food
# 也是粤菜一种常用的调料
It’s also a common ingredient in Cantonese food
# 这个网上都有卖的
You can buy it online
# 你看味道不一样吧
Look, the smell is quite different
# 这个喼汁 25克
25g of Worcestershire Sauce
# 大爷你看 也都搁进去
Mix it in, Da Ye
# 这喼汁和OK汁俩出来有种特殊的合成香味
The Worcestershire Sauce and OK Sauce create an incredibly unique aroma
# 混合味道
The combination of flavours
# 镇江香醋60克
60g of Zhenjiang vinegar
# 然后冰糖搁一块就够了
One piece of rock sugar
# 冰糖少搁点
Don’t add too much rock sugar
# 是吧
Right?
# 这还有一个呢 红曲水
And of course, the stock of red yeast rice
# 找颜色
To give the dish its colour
# 红曲水 提前沏好的
We have boiled it earlier
# 市场上有卖红曲粉红曲米
You can find red yeast powder or red yeast rice in the market
# 经过提前要泡制
And you need to boil it before using it
# 然后我们打点水 烧烧它
Then, we add in some water
# 烧开了的热水4勺
4 ladles of boiling water
# 大爷我们先烧它一会
Let’s braise the dish for some time
# 齐活
Now it’s ready
# 高压锅吧 师父
Transfer them to the high-pressure cooker
# 你压上锅我这菜就可以上了
Once done, I can serve the dish
# 你看见没有 这颜色也挺漂亮
Look at the colour, how beautiful
# 好
Great
# 得了大爷 非常漂亮
Da Ye, they look gorgeous
# 无锡排骨
Wuxi Pork Ribs
# 开始压
Pressure on
# 时间到25分钟
Time is up, 25 minutes
# 出锅
Take it out
# 大爷您快闻闻这个味
Smell it, Da Ye
# 非常特殊
Very special
# 错不了
It can’t go wrong
# 把排骨先捡出来
Take out the ribs first
# 先把配料给它煸炒一下
Let’s fry some other ingredients
# 先给它煸熟了它
Fry them first until they are cooked
# 煸一下辅料
Fry these minor ingredients
# 对
Yes
# 青红椒
Green and red bell peppers
# 还有洋葱
And onions
# 好 马上放到小盆里头
OK, transfer them into a small bowl
# 来 师父
Come, master
# 您把这汁往下一倒就行了
You may just pour the sauce here
# 再加点生抽 找找口儿
Add some light soy sauce for seasoning
# 这颜色已经挺漂亮了
The colour is already so appetising
# 又加点生抽啊
Some more light soy sauce
# 大概有6克的生抽
Roughly 6g of it
# 这排骨闻着就香啊
The pork ribs smell so good
# 蜂蜜
Add honey
# 有10克就足够
10g are enough
# 原有基础上又加了一勺白糖
Another spoonful of caster sugar
# 咸味够了
It’s perfectly savoury
# 砂锅我给烧上了啊
Heat the stone bowl
# 生活要有仪式感
We need this sense of ceremony in life
# 这味道多香啊
How fragrant it is!
# 味道特殊
Such a unique flavour
# 口儿合适
It’s nicely balanced
# 这过年过节的时候来这么一锅
Cook this during holidays
# 港派无锡骨
Wuxi Pork Ribs in Hong Kong style
# 它是咸鲜能吃出来
You can taste the savouriness
# 甜酸也能吃出来
As well as the sweetness and sourness
# 还有一种特殊的香味
And it also has a unique aroma
# 这喼汁应该是外来的调味品
This Worcestershire Sauce is an imported seasoning
# 这回差不多
It’s almost done now
# 好
Right
# 准备勾芡咯
Let’s add the slurry now
# 这就得是喝红酒了大爷 是吧
You must drink some red wine with this dish right, Da Ye?
# 吃肉喝红酒
Red wine with the meat
# 很漂亮
So beautiful
# 来点明油
A splash of oil
# 精彩
Brilliant
# 对明油亮芡儿
Bright oil goes so well with the slurry
# 好
Alright
# 出锅了
The dish is now served
# 看看 冒泡儿
Look at all these bubbles
# 好了 漂亮啊
It looks absolutely fantastic
# 醋的香气 OK汁的香气
The aroma from vinegar and OK Sauce is amazing
# 大爷给您来块肉吃
Try some ribs, Da Ye
# 这立秋我都没吃过肉
I haven’t had any meat since the start of autumn
# 来点汁
A bit of sauce
# 港式的啊
Hong Kong style
# 我每次都是享受第一口的幸福
I’m always blessed to be the first to try
# 幸福满满
Full of happiness
# 港式无锡排骨
Wuxi Pork Ribs in Hong Kong style
# 大爷直摇头
Da Ye is moving his head around
# 大爷回味
Da Ye is recollecting the pleasant flavour
# 我在比较
I’m comparing it
# 跟无锡排骨有什么不同
With the traditional Wuxi Pork Ribs to see what makes this different
# 咸 甜 酸 鲜
Savoury, sweet, sour and umami
# 汁儿香 味厚
The sauce is fragrant, and the flavour is bold
# 跟无锡排骨有截然不同的比较
It’s indeed so different from the traditional Wuxi Pork Ribs
# 我这心砰吱砰吱直跳
My heart is beating so hard
# 你说大爷就做南方菜
You know, Da Ye is so good at cooking Southern food
# 不是 有什么说什么
To be honest
# 各有千秋
They both taste great
# 二伯这点我比较信服在哪呢
The best thing about Er Bai’s cooking is that
# 二伯不管做鸡
When Er Bai cooks chicken
# 没有鸡味
You won’t taste the gamey flavour of chicken
# 做排骨没有排骨味
And when he cooks pork ribs, you won’t taste the gamey flavour of pork
# 说什么味儿呢
So what flavours do they have?
# 说白了就是
What I really mean is that
# 鸡的腥味
The gamey flavours of chicken
# 排骨的腥味
pork
# 鸡鸭的腥味
Duck
# 包括其他的一些牛肉羊肉的腥味没有
And all other meats like beef and lamb are gone
# 为什么
Why?
# 他巧妙地运用了胡萝卜
Er Bai cleverly utilises the carrots
# 芹菜
Celeries
# 香菜
Coriander
# 葱头
And spring onions
# 荤素搭配合理
So the balance of meat and vegetables
# 颜色搭配合理
Colours
# 口味搭配合理
And flavours is just spot on
# 不管是港式的 苏式的
Regardless of Hong Kong or Jiangsu style
# 各有千秋
They are both delicious
# 说个不同的吧 我也透露一下
Let’s talk about something different. I’ll reveal
# 无锡排骨的方法
How traditional Wuxi Pork Ribs are made
# 无锡排骨不炸
We don’t fry the ribs in the traditional way
# 为什么不炸呢
Why not?
# 他需要吃排骨的软烂
Because we want the ribs to be soft and tender
# 你看
Look
# 二伯做这排骨
The ribs Er Bai made
# 看着软烂
Seem soft
# 但是很整齐
But they are actually quite firm
# 因为它拿油给炸了
Because the ribs have been fried
# 排骨保持着完整性
So they maintain their shapes very well
# 锁住水分
The juice has been locked in the meat
# 但是它瘦而不柴
They are lean but not dry
# 淮扬菜你比如说糖醋排骨
Some other dishes like sweet and sour pork ribs
# 它也要炸
Also need to be fried first
# 但是它做什么
But they are served
# 做冷菜
As a cold entree
# 糖醋小排
Sweet and sour pork ribs
# 那个要炸要吃什么肉的干香
Are fried to bring out their fragrance
# 然后回甜
Sweet aftertaste
# 还有醋的醋香
And the aroma from the vinegar
# 二伯这个手法呢我特别赞同也欣赏
I’m definitely convinced by the way how Er Bai cooks the ribs, and I love it
# 二伯 辛苦
Good job, Er Bai
# 谢谢大爷
Much appreciated, Da Ye
# 终于能让大爷赞美一句 不容易
It’s not easy to have Da Ye’s compliments
# 评价师父呢 小心点
Be careful when you comment on your master’s dish
# 又吃那老味儿了师父
It reminds me of the old flavours, master
# 跟原来您教我那个一样
It’s the same as what you have taught me
# 过两天我回家再做一份
I’ll cook this dish again once I go back home in a few days
# 港式无锡骨
Wuxi Pork Ribs in Hong Kong style
# 感谢师父 感谢大爷
Thanks master, and thanks Da Ye
# 非常好
Very nice
# 二伯踏实了
Er Bai can get relaxed now
# 二伯尝尝吧
Help yourself, Er Bai
# 以前的小吃现在不太常见了
This is a dessert from the old days, and it’s not as common now
# 老北京果子干
Old Beijing braised dried fruits
# 您看看咱们今天准备的料
Have a look at our ingredients today
# 柿饼 葡萄干 山楂干 杏干
Dried persimmons, raisins, dried Chinese hawthorns, dried apricots
# 圣女果干这是新的
And dried cherry tomatoes. They are the new ingredients
# 这个是咱们在传统的基础上
Yes, they are the creative addition
# 又加以创新了
To our old tradition
# 还有藕 这个藕是我刚才削的
These are lotuses which I just peeled
# 然后您看不变色为什么呢
Why didn’t they turn black?
# 刚才我在这水里边加了点白醋
Because I added white vinegar into the water just now
# 桂花 然后这还有糖桂花
Osmanthus. Yes, here is some osmanthus syrup
# 咱们网友在家的时候把这些都得洗洗
When you cook this dish at home, remember to rinse these ingredients
# 把它泡开了 是为了褶皱里边的
Soak them first, so we can rinse out the dirt
# 有点脏东西给它洗出来
Hidden in the wrinkles
# 全都把这些泡上
Soak all of them
# 咱们这柿饼要拿手掰 不要切
Shred these dried persimmons by hand instead of chopping them
# 把这藕咱们切一下 九个眼的
Let’s slice these lotuses. They are nine-eyed
# 咱们把这藕焯一下 锅一开就可以了
Then, blanch them and take them out as soon as the water is boiling
# 准备一盆凉水 这里边加点白醋
Get a bowl of cold water with some white vinegar
# 为了防止藕变黑
To stop the lotuses from turning black
# 水开了冲凉吗 不用冲凉里边有醋
Do we need to rinse them with cold water after blanching? No, because of the white vinegar in the water
# 普及一个小知识
Some facts about lotus
# 九眼藕含淀粉量高 炖出来以后是面糊的
Nine-eyed lotuses have the highest amount of starch, so they are quite glutinous after braising
# 基本上产在长江以南
They are mostly grown in the south of Yangtze River
# 北方的藕脆甜嫩
And the lotuses in the north are crunchy, sweet and tender
# 荷塘小炒那就得是用脆藕 它是七眼的
The dish Stir-fried Lotus uses those crunchy lotuses, which are seven-eyed
# 水也开了 山楂下去 这个先煮一会
Now the water is boiling. Put in the dried hawthorns first and boil them for a bit
# 然后把杏干下去
Then add in dried apricots
# 葡萄干 圣女果干
Raisins, dried cherry tomatoes
# 把冰塘下去 黄冰糖
And rock sugar, yellow rock sugar to be exact
# 咱们把柿饼给掰成这么大块就行了
Then let’s shred the dried persimmons into big pieces like this
# 一定要拿手掰 别切
Make sure to shred them by hand rather than chopping them
# 切的没有掰的口感好
Shredded persimmons have the better texture than the chopped ones
# 把它熬粘稠了就行了
Braise them until they are sticky
# 把这柿饼搁里边 全名叫什么来着
Add in these dried persimmons. What is this dish called?
# 叫果子干
Braised dried fruits
# 以前都是挑着担子
In the old days, vendors would carry them on the shoulder
# 果子干儿嘞
And yell “braised dried fruits”
# 您看这个水变这个颜色了
Look, the colour of the water has changed
# 把这藕也下去
Now add in the lotuses
# 这果子干有什么固定要求么
What are the fixed ingredients for this dish?
# 基本上就是这几样
Basically what we have here
# 咱这儿还有一个秘密武器 这是果冻粉
And we also have a secret weapon, jelly powder
# 咱们加一点水先把它化开了
Mix it in the water first
# 其实咱们汤汁已经有点黏度了
The juice is already somewhat syrupy
# 加上这个口感更好
It will have an even better texture with this added in
# 藕粉呢 藕粉也可以
How about lotus powder? It works as well
# 咱们在网上都能买得到
They all can be purchased online
# 咱这样就把火关上
That’s it. Turn off the heat
# 咱们准备了点干桂花 这点就够了
We have some dried osmanthus here, which is well enough
# 咱们把它搁里边
Add it into the pot
# 把它晾凉以后 下入冰箱
Cool them down before transferring them into the fridge
# 桂花酱还没放呢 最后出锅时再放
We haven’t added the osmanthus syrup yet. Wait until they are taken out of the pot
# 这个味道非常好 等到自然凉确之后
They look so tasty. Once they are naturally cooled down
# 往冰箱一放  明天早上一吃
Chuck the pot in the fridge for enjoying tomorrow morning
# 大爷您看 咱们从冰箱里边
Look, Da Ye, we have taken the pot out of the fridge
# 冰镇完了拿出来了
They have been nicely chilled
# 我给您盛一碗 藕现在还是脆的呢
I’ll serve you a bowl. Lotuses are still crunchy
# 我知道您爱吃甜的
I know you love desserts
# 特意给您来点 桂花酱
Some osmanthus syrup for you
# 您尝尝合不合您的口味
Have a taste to see if you like it
# 我就来个柿饼吃吧 酸酸甜甜
I’ll eat some persimmons first. They are sweet and sour
# 大爷爱吃柿饼是吧
Da Ye loves dried persimmons
# 真好吃
It’s really delicious
# 酸的脆的甜的 各种味道融合在一块
It’s sour, crunchy and sweet. Such a beautiful combination of different flavours
# 你看二伯 谁爱吃甜的啊
Look at Er Bai. Now we know who truly loves desserts
# 二伯那碗儿快吃完了
Er Bai is almost finishing his bowl
# 尤其那藕 脆脆的
Especially these lotuses, so crunchy
# 还带有淡淡的桂花香气
With hints of fragrance from the osmanthus
# 甜食本身就抓人 酸甜开胃
Dessert is attractive in itself. It’s sweet and sour, and opens up your appetite
# 到夏天冰碗它又特别解暑
It also chills you down so well in summer
# 生产大块冰 小碗一碗碗的全搁在冰上
Get a large piece of ice, and place small bowls of this dish all on the ice
# 来一碗清凉爽口
Have a bowl, nice and chilled
# 那个炎热的夏天
In the hot summer
# 北京人的情怀
This is the nostalgia of Beijingers